A Guide to the Patricia F. Parthree Collection on Mount Vernon High School, 1950-2012
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Patricia F. Parthree Collection on Mount Vernon High School, 1950-2012
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-95
3.0 linear feet
The Patricia F. Parthree Collection on Mount Vernon High School consists of 3.0 linear feet and spans the years 1950-2012 and contains class photographs, certificates, graduation invitations, correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, a notebook, school songs and chants, code of ethics, letterhead, tickets, programs, school newspapers, school literary magazine, student directory, school jacket, pin, pennant, and a school logo patch. Subjects covered are Mount Vernon High School and student life in Fairfax County, Virginia.
Parthree, Patricia F. (1937-2012)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Cindy Blass, daughter of Patricia Parthree on December 5, 2015.
Historical and Biographical Information
Patricia Faith Vines was born on March 20, 1937 in Washington D.C. and adopted by Homer H. and Myrtle P. Vines of Alabama. Shortly thereafter, the family moved to Arlington, Virginia and later the Jefferson Manor neighborhood in Alexandria.
In 1950, Pat enrolled in Mount Vernon High School as an eighth grader. She partook in several extracurricular activities and school clubs including Junior Commercial Club, Barber Shop Quartet, and Patrol. She also participated in Glee Club during her entire academic career there.
As a sophomore in July 1953, Pat signed up to be a nurse aid for the summer at Alexandria Hospital. She took a two-week high school nurse aid course prior to spending her entire summer at the hospital.
After she graduated in 1955, Pat secured a secretarial job for the Department of the Army. On February 14, 1959 Pat married her high school sweetheart, Donald Cletus Parthree (MVHS Class of 1956). The couple moved to Baltimore, Maryland for a short period where Donald worked as a meatpacker for Esskay Meat Products. Feeling homesick, they moved back to Springfield, Virginia where Pat resumed her Pentagon job as a secretary for the Department of the Army.
In 1967, the Parthrees moved to Waldorf, Maryland where Pat stayed at home and raised their three children, Dawn, Cindy and Greg. When the youngest child reached school age, Pat went back to work as a secretary for the Charles County public schools system. After a period of years, she returned to the government as a secretary for the Department of the Navy at the Naval Surface Warfare Center in Indian Head, Maryland. She retired in September 2003. Pat was also a charter member and pianist of the First Baptist Church of St. Charles. She passed away on November 4, 2012.
Scope and Content
Series 1: Personal, 1953-1966, Boxes 1 and 4
Contains personal materials of Patricia F. (Vines) Parthree including photographs of her Mount Vernon High School classmates, certificates, graduation invitations, a letter, newsletter, English class notebook, and her Mount Vernon High School Majors jacket. Certificates comprise of one AAA issued School Safety Patrol Award of Merit to Pat Vines and a Mount Vernon High School Stadium Lights stock certificate issued to Pat’s husband, Donald C. Parthree. Class photographs are portraits of Mount Vernon High School students from the 1953-1954 school year. The Progress Notes newsletter mentions Pat Vines signing up to be a nurse aid at Alexandria Hospital.
Series 2: Ephemera and Memorabilia, 1954-1955, Boxes 1 and 4
Contains Mount Vernon High School memorabilia including the Last Will and Testament from the Class of 1955, articles of proclamation, school songs and chants, code of ethics, letterhead, school patch, a pin, and a pennant. Also contained is a Pabst Blue Ribbon napkin printed with the beer company’s theme song. The Articles of Proclamation were written by students in the Mt. Vernon Majors calling for fellow classmates to not show up for class on Veterans Day 1954 since the school did not recognize it as a national holiday.
Series 3: Events, 1951-1972, Box 1
Contains materials from Mount Vernon High School sponsored events. Items mainly consist of programs and tickets from dances, graduations, sporting events, school clubs, and other school events. Items from non-school events held in the surrounding Mount Vernon area include a ticket from the S.S. Mt. Vernon and Mt. Vernon Drive-in theatre.
Series 4: School Publications, 1950-1955, Boxes 1 and 2
Contains Mount Vernon High School student publications including issues of the school newspaper Em Vee Hi, the student newsletter The Little Major, the student handbook Spyglass, the school’s literary magazine The Ink Blotch, and an undated student directory.
Series 5: Newspaper Clippings, 1955-2012, Box 2
Contains newspaper clippings relating to Mount Vernon High School. Subjects include mostly obituaries of former students but also a variety of 1950s clippings about the school‘s buildings and student activities.
Series 6: Reunion Materials, 1983-2006, Boxes 2, 3, and 4
Contains materials for reunions held for Mount Vernon High School alumni. Subjects include the Class of 1955, Class of 1956, and the 50th Anniversary of the school. Items include reunion papers, reunion books, correspondence, pins, tickets, notes, and alumni lists.
Arrangement
Series 1: Personal, 1953-1966, Boxes 1 and 4
Series 2: Ephemera and Memorabilia, 1954-1955, Boxes 1 and 4
Series 3: Events, 1951-1972, Box 1
Series 4: School Publications, 1950-1955, Boxes 1 and 2
Series 5: Newspaper Clippings, 1955-2012, Box 2
Series 6: Reunion Materials, 1983-2006, Boxes 2, 3, and 4
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Mount Vernon High School Collection, MSS 11-13
The Surveyor 1951-1955 yearbooks removed and added to the yearbook collection.
Index Terms
Alexandria, Va.; Fairfax County Public Schools; Fairfax County, Va. - Education; Mount Vernon High School (Alexandria, Va.); Parthree, Donald C.; Parthree, Patricia F. (Vines)
Container List
- Series 1: Personal, 1953-1966
  - Jacket. Mount Vernon High School Majors, c. 1950s (Box 4)
  - Class Photographs, "My School Pals", 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter, Progress Notes. [Pat Vines mentioned], 1954 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter, Leah Van Scoyoc to Pat Vines, Re: Travel De Lux Party, 1954 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "English Notebook", 1954 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificate, School Safety Patrol Award of Merit to Patricia Vines, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Graduation Announcements and receipt for Patricia Faith Vines, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stock Certificate, Mount Vernon High School Stadium Lights, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Ephemera and Memorabilia, 1954-1955
  - Articles of Proclamation for recognition of Veterans Day, 1954 November (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1955 Last Will and Testament, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Napkin, Pabst Blue Ribbon theme song, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - School Songs and Chants, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Code of Ethics, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mount Vernon High School letterhead, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mount Vernon High School logo patch, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mount Vernon High School pin, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mount Vernon High School pennant, Undated (Box 4)
- Series 3: Events, 1951-1972
  - Program, Mount Vernon High School Glee Club Christmas Program, 1951 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Program, Commencement Exercises, 1952 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Program, Spring Concert, 1953 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Program, Dedication of Mount Vernon High School, 1953 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Program, Annual Christmas Program, 1954 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Program and ticket, Choral Music Festival District IV Virginia High Schools, 1955 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Program and ticket, "The Late Christopher Bean" Senior class play, 1955 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ticket, Junior Senior Prom, 1955 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Program, Baccalaureate Service [3 programs], 1955 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Program, ticket, speech, and itinerary, Class Night Exercises, 1955 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Program and ticket, Senior Banquet, 1955 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Program, Commencement Exercises [2 programs], 1955 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Napkin and card, Sno-Ball Dance, 1955 December 21 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Program, "January Thaw" Senior Class play, 1956 February 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Program and memorabilia, Melvin B. Landes Appreciation Night, 1972 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Program, Talent Show, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ticket, Washington-Lee High School Athletic Association, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Program cover and football schedule, Fairfax Rebels vs. Mount Vernon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Scrapbook Page, Music Festival, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ticket, S.S. Mt. Vernon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ticket, Mt. Vernon Drive-In Theatre, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Series 4: School Publications, 1950-1955
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1950 March (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1950 October (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1950 November (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1950 December (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Student Newsletter, The Little Major, 1950 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1951 March (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1951 April (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1951 May (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Student Newsletter, The Little Major, 1951 June 01 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1951 October (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1951 November (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1951 December (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Student Handbook, Spyglass, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1952 January (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi [2 copies], 1952 February (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1952 March (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1952 April (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1952 June (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1954 October (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1954 November (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1954 December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Student Handbook, Spyglass, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1955 January (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1955 February (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1955 March (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1955 June (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper, Em Vee Hi, 1955 April (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Literary Magazine, The Ink Blotch, 1955 May (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Student Directory, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 5: Newspaper Clippings, 1955-2012
  - Miscellaneous Mount Vernon High School clippings, c. 1950s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Nelson Coe of Area is Killed", 1955 December (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Obituary for Joseph A. Jacobs, 1984 August 19 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Obituary for Gene Steinbach, 1993 August 10 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Obituary for Catherine P. Cooley, 1995 August 16 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Obituary for Melvin Bowman Landes, 2004 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Obituary for Frederick H. "Boom Boom" Cameron Sr., 2005 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Obituary for Gary Eugene Treon, 2008 March 30 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Obituary for Lucy Jane Lowman, 2012 January 31 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series 6: Reunion Materials, 1983-2006
  - 1983 Class of 1955 28th Reunion, 1983 June 25 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mug, Class of 1955 28th Reunion, 1983 June 25 (Box 3)
  - Mount Vernon High School 50th Anniversary Gala Celebration, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1993 Class of 1955 38th Reunion, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 2002 Class of 1955 Reunion, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 2005 Class of 1955 50th Reunion, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 2006 Class of 1956 50th Reunion, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Mug, Class of 1956 50th Reunion, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Tote Bag, Class of 1956 50th Reunion, 2006 (Box 4)